<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lawfulnes of tithes demonstrated to the convincing of such of the Quakers as pretend conscience against the payment of them, or, A demonstration for liberty of conscience to the Quakers in the payment of their tithes by W.J.</title>
            <author>Jeffery, William, 1616-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08776569</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08776569</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41771</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46714)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41771)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1262:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lawfulnes of tithes demonstrated to the convincing of such of the Quakers as pretend conscience against the payment of them, or, A demonstration for liberty of conscience to the Quakers in the payment of their tithes by W.J.</title>
                  <author>Jeffery, William, 1616-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Williams,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: Country-men and friends call'd Quakers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41771:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LAWFULNES OF TITHES, Demonſtrated to the Convincing of ſuch of the <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS</hi> as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Conſcience againſt the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them: OR, A Demonſtration for LIBERTY of CONSCIENCE to the <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS</hi> in the Payment of their TITHES.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. J.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>It is a Snare to the Man that devoureth that which is Holy, and after Vows to make Enquiry,
<bibl>Prov. 20.25.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John VVilliams,</hi> in <hi>Croſs-Key-Court</hi> in <hi>Little Brittain,</hi> 1675</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:41771:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41771:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE COURTEOUS READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et me find thee ſuch as I beſpeak thee, Courteous. Be not offended with this little Treatiſe at the firſt ſight of it, being ſo ſmall upon ſuch a Subject of concern; and of the which ſome Learned Men have writ already. It is ſmall, becauſe it is deſign'd for the uſe of thoſe that are
<pb facs="tcp:41771:3"/>wont to read but ſmall Books, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the meaner ſort of <hi>Quakers.</hi> It treats upon this Subject, not that I think to doe any great feats by it, but that it may mind thoſe that are Learned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to undertake this, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things (wherein the <hi>Quakers</hi> do diſturb the Church) proving not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lawfulneſs of Tithes, <hi>viz.</hi> that they may be paid, (which I do) but alſo the neceſſity of them, that they ought to be paid, or at leaſtwiſe the Expediency of them, that they are beſt to be paid. The aime of ſuch Learned Men as have writ of this Subject already, was not the Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> (of whom they did not ſo much as dream) but the Confirmation of Princes and Rulers, to continue in the Land,
<pb facs="tcp:41771:3"/>and Nation ſuch Goſpel-Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as was of ſo long ſtanding, and had been ſo well begun: Now theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> being to be ſatisfied (if any thing will do it) require this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be managed another way, if not for matter, yet for manner, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and ſtile, which I leave to the Diſcretion of ſuch of the Learned, as shall have the Charity to travail with theſe poor Men (with the will of God) to reduce, and bring them back to the Eſtablishment, and Peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>As St. <hi>Paul</hi> did acknowledge himſelf to be Debtor to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and to the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> to the Wiſe, and to the Unwiſe: So I think (under Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that the Learned in the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities and elſe-where, are Debtors in
<pb facs="tcp:41771:4"/>theſe dayes unto all the Sects that are among us, <hi>viz.</hi> to endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them: Among the which Sects, theſe of the <hi>Quakers</hi> (if it may rightly be called a Sect) and not rather a Rage, and a Tumult fomeing out their own shame: I ſay, this ſuch as it is, is not to be let go <hi>in malam rem,</hi> as deſperate as it ſeems to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Again, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> profeſt that he was ready to preach the Goſpel to them which were at <hi>Rome</hi> alſo; ſo I hope our Learned men will not diſdain to take pains with theſe <hi>Quakers,</hi> though they be gone from us as far as <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Gain-ſaying of Tith, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out Hireling, is the main thing they cant withal; therein applying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the humor of ſuch as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phainly Covetous amongſt us.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41771:4"/>
            <p>The more unlearned this Sect of Quaking is, the greater learning it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires for the Confuting of it; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not to be wrought upon otherwiſe than by Demonſtrations; which I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, Learning, Leaſure, and Libraries may be able to make out unto them, by shewing them, as a Perpetuity of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and a Maintenance to it: So alſo a propriety both of the one, and of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and this to be deduced through the whole Series of times, and ages; the univerſalities of People and Nations; and the variety of Empires, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments.</p>
            <p>This little Tract was devis'd by me for the ſatisfaction of a private Man, my Neighbour: Why I have made it publique, I have given an account al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; namely, to mind ſuch as are
<pb facs="tcp:41771:5"/>Learned, and have leaſure from Week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sermons to travail, as they do with the other Sects that are among us; ſo alſo with thoſe poor Men called <hi>Quakers:</hi> I ſay, to mind them; for it's posſible they hear not the clamours and out-cries of theſe Men, as poor Incumbents do. How good a Work the turning men from the Errour of their ways may be, appears by the great Good St. <hi>James</hi> pronounces to come of it. Reader, recommend this good Work to whom thou think'ſt it proper. Be Friendly, and Farewel.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41771:5"/>
            <head>COUNTRY-MEN and FRIENDS CALL'D QUAKERS</head>
            <p>§. 1. TO your Queſtion demanding by what Right <hi>Tythes</hi> become due in the Church of <hi>England?</hi>
               <note place="margin">As a ſick man is cur'd of his diſeaſe by vertue of a Medicine; ſo is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil man heal'd of his malice by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Law. <hi>Pythagoras.</hi> Break not the Laws made for the wealth of the Country. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> Endeavour thy ſelf to keep the Law, that God may be pleaſed with thee. <hi>Ariſtot.</hi>
               </note> I anſwer, that it is by the Law of the Land; which being not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Law of God, ought to be obey'd by every Subject. Now this Law of our Land is not only according to the Law of God, but alſo fitted to it, and deviſed by it.</p>
            <p>That there was a Law for <hi>Tythes</hi> under the Old Teſtament, there is no Man doubts.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lex vetus de Sabbato,</hi> &amp;c. The Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sabbath, and the other concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tythes (in the Old Teſtament) do ſhew that Chriſtians are oblig'd to ſet apart no leſs than the ſeventh day for God's Worſhip and Service; nor leſs than the tenth part of their fruits or encreaſe, for the maintenance of thoſe that are Chriſts Miniſters. <hi>Grot. de Jure Bell. &amp; Pac.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 1.</note> That that Law is ſtill abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi> for the Subſtance and Equity of it, under the Goſpel, That is it which ſome Men would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ignorant of. But I prove it thus:</p>
            <p>What was in being both for Right and Practice before the Law was given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and in that Law was expreſt, and ſet forth, and hath not been forbidden ſince, nor any way abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated; that is abiding ſtill: But ſuch is the Law for <hi>Tythes,</hi> therefore it is ſtill abiding.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:41771:6"/>
            <p>That it was in being before the Law was given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> appears by <hi>Abraham</hi> paying <hi>Tythes</hi> to <hi>Melchiſedek,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi> (l. 4. c. xxxiv.) and <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> cap. xvi. uſe this Law, in proving the Equity of Tyth under the Goſpel, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, He Tythed <hi>Abraham, (i e.)</hi> he took Tyth upon him, <hi>viz.</hi> of his Goods; which implyes, that the one was in Duty bound to pay it, and the other had a Right to demand and take it. The Text ſaith, <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedek</hi> met <hi>Abraham:</hi> Wherefore? to beg an Alms of him? No, but to receive his Due from him. O how fain would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Miſers have the Clergy brought unto their Alms! on purpoſe, that they might deal by them, as <hi>Judas</hi> would have done by our Saviour Chriſt. See <hi>Calvin</hi>'s complaint in this caſe. <hi>Abraham</hi> did not this by any politick Conſtitution, nor by any Right of Ceremony: Therefore it was by the Law of Nature that he did it.</note> Gen. 14.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Text hath not [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] but [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] It ſaith not that <hi>Abraham</hi> brought to <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> ſomewhat in Gift, but that he gave him that part and portion which was due unto him. If he had been free either to give, or not to give, then in giving, he would have given what he had pleas'd, and not have been bound to divide. A Diviſion is of one whole thing into parts, which needeth not, but when ſome part is due out of it.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> had no other Right to what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from <hi>Abraham,</hi> but only of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Bounty, and good will; then how doth St. <hi>Paul</hi> prefer his Prieſt-hood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that of the Sons of <hi>Levi?</hi> For they had a Right, and a Law to receive what they did from the People, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Again, If he had no Right or Authority to receive any thing from <hi>Abraham,</hi> then was not he greater than <hi>Abraham:</hi> For I may humble my ſelf to give what I pleaſe, to whom I pleaſe; but I am inferiour only where I am ſubject, and bound to pay.</p>
            <p>But you'l ſay, by what Right did <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> receive <hi>Tith,</hi> or for what? For Sacrificing? No, (we do not Read that he did any ſuch thing) but for Bleſſing: <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> pay'd the Tenth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41771:6"/>
            <p>Hereupon I aſſume thus: <hi>Tyths</hi> were due unto <hi>Melchiſedek,</hi> not for Sacrificing, but for Bleſſing only: Therefore <hi>Tyths</hi> do remain due under the Goſpel upon the ſame account. The conſequence I prove, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12. The Law concerning Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is not changed, except the Prieſt-hood be changed alſo: But the Prieſt-hood of Chriſt, and that of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dek</hi> is the ſame, therefore the ſame Law remaineth under both.</p>
            <p>You'l object again; What was <hi>Abraham</hi> but a ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? What he did, he did for himſelf, and what is that to Us?</p>
            <p>Not ſo: <hi>Abraham</hi> was the Father of the Faithful, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> he paying Tyth to <hi>Melchiſedek,</hi> did ſhadow or repreſent all the Faithful under the Goſpel, paying Tith to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Abraham</hi> I might go to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and take him vowing a Vow, the ſubject whereof was, that if the Lord would be with him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.20.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then ſhould the Lord be his God: The ſtone which he ſet for a Pillar ſhould be God's Houſe; and of all that God ſhould give him, he would give the Tenth unto God. If <hi>Jacob</hi> had not very well known this Vow of his to be grounded upon good Right on God's part, and Duty on his own; he would never have made it.</p>
            <p>Is not the ſame Right on God's part ſtill, and the ſame Duty on ours? Is it not God that gives us all that we have,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt enim hoc conſcientiae noſtrae vulgare &amp; commune Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium,</hi> &amp;c. It is a common Teſtimony of our Conſcience known even to the Heathens, that the Neceſſaries of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life are to be beg'd of God: From whence it is, that even a mongſt the Gentiles Tyths of all things were vow'd unto <hi>Hercules. Lambert Danaeus de Oratione Dominica<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> pa. 154.</note> and ought not we to acknowledge him as <hi>Jacob</hi> did.</p>
            <p>To acknowledge God in this caſe, is not a Will-worſhip of ours, but a Doctrine taught by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41771:7"/>
               <hi>Honour God with thy ſubſtance, and with the firſt Fruits of all thine Increaſe.</hi> Though <hi>Solomon</hi> was not in being when <hi>Jacob</hi> was, yet the Holy Ghoſt was; and if he had not been <hi>Iacob</hi>'s Teacher in the making of this Vow, this Vow ſhould not have been Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Scriptures to the Commendation of him as it is: Yea, what hindr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me to ſay, that it is written not only for his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, but alſo for our Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there being all the
<note n="*" place="margin">Saith St. <hi>Aug. Quid enim ſi diceret Deus,</hi> &amp;c. What if God ſhould ſay, Thou art mine, O man, the ground which thou tilleſt is mine; the Seeds which thou ſoweſt, the Beaſts which thou wearieſt are mine; the Rain is mine, and ſo is the Heat of the Sun: Seeing all theſe things are mine, thou which only lendeſt thy Hand to the Work, deſerveſt hardly the Tenth: But I keep Nine parts for thee, give me the Tenth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Equity that may be, that we ſhould do as he hath done?</p>
            <p>Nay, This Leſſon is ſtill taught by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Let him that is taught in the word, communicate unto him that teacheth in all good things.</hi> Here is an expreſs command of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things in Kind under the Goſpel. Indeed the word [Tith] or [Tenth] is not here ſet down; perhaps becauſe that part or portion is ſuppos'd to be notoriouſly known. As it is not for Chriſtians to ſtrive about words, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4. ſo I think it is not for them to ſtrive for want of Words, where the things themſelves that are in Queſtion are to be found in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. To ſtrive for want of Words, what is it but to dote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Queſtions? Thoſe that oppoſe Tyths for want of having them nam'd in the New Teſtament, ſeem in this to be like thoſe that oppos'd the Conſubſtantiality of the Perſons in the Deity, becauſe the Word [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] is not to be found in the Scripture: And yet the Word [Tything] is to be found in the New Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> ſpoken by our Saviour Chriſt himſelf, and that aſſerting the Right of Tythes, ſaying, that they ought to be pay'd. If you ſay they ought to be pay'd then, but not now, I ask where it is that our Saviour hath told you ſo, or what cauſe is there that it ſhould be ſo?</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41771:7"/>
            <p>Our Saviour declar'd unto the <hi>Jews</hi> that he was Lord even of the Sabbath, <hi>i. e.</hi> that he had Power given him, to ſet his People free from the Neceſſity of obſerving the Sabbath; or at leaſtwiſe to moderate them in the Obſervation of it: But of Tyth he ſaid no ſuch thing. It was propheſi'd, that the Jewiſh Sabbath ſhould ceaſe to be; but of Tythes there is no ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy. The continuance of that Sabbath might not conſiſt with Chriſt exhibited, but Tythes may, being no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Liberty, wherewith Chriſt hath made us free. If you pay not the tenth, you will pay ſome other part, <hi>viz.</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or leſs: More we do not challenge,
<note place="margin">The Heathens judg'd it reaſonable, that thoſe which ſerv'd at their Idol-Altars, ſhould live thereof: The proportion of Tyth or Tenth they might borrow from the Patriarchs the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it among the Nations.</note> Leſs you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pay, except you will not only alter God's Proportion, but alſo have leſs regard to the juſt Maintenance of your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters under the New Teſtament, than the People of God had of theirs under the Old. As if theſe were not as worthy to live of the Goſpel, as thoſe others were to live of the Altar.</p>
            <p>Thus I have done with the firſt Member of my Argument, in the fifting whereof I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſuch Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of you,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> is moſt probably thought to be <hi>Sem,</hi> the eldeſt Son of <hi>Noah,</hi> who liv'd in the Dayes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and by his Primoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture had Right to take Tyths even of him.</note> as may beſpeak you not only Civil, but alſo Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Now of the ſecond Member, <hi>viz.</hi> That it was expreſt, and ſet forth in the Law given by <hi>Moſes:</hi> And this I prove from <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.30. <hi>Num.</hi> 18.8. and 31.2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.4.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc jure Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. By this Law (<hi>viz.</hi> of Nature) <hi>Abraham</hi> gave the tenth to God of thoſe ſpoyls which he took from the five Kings mentioned in <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. &amp;c. <hi>Quo more Graeci quoque,</hi> &amp;c. Aud by the ſame Law alſo, the <hi>Graecians, Cartbaginians,</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> dedicated the Tenth of their ſpoyls to <hi>Apollo, Hercules, Jupiter Feretrius,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Grot. de jur. Belli &amp; Pacis</hi> lib. 3. cap. 6.</note> My Inference here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence is this: <hi>Moſes, Num.</hi> 18.8. makes the Faculty of receiving Tyth to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41771:8"/>belong unto the Prieſt-hood or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry by reaſon of the Anoynting, <hi>i. e.</hi> their Calling. In the 31. <hi>verſe,</hi> he makes it to belong unto them, becauſe of their Work or Service: But both the Calling and Work of the Miniſtry do ſtill abide: Therefore alſo the Faculty of receiving Tyths, which is the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the one, and the Reward of the other. The Minor I prove, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 Chron. 31.4. <hi>Commanded the People that dwelt at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to give their Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Prieſts,
<note place="margin">As <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was ſingularly commended among the Kings of <hi>Judah:</hi> So did the ſingularity of his Commendation conſiſt in this, <hi>viz.</hi> that he was moſt zealous for Religion and Piety, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.</note> &amp; to the Levites, that they might be Encouraged in the Law of the Lord.</hi> From whence I Argue thus:</p>
            <p>What was well done of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> by the Miniſters of the Law, that is well done ſtill of godly Princes by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel;
<note place="margin">Upon this account it is, that he is ſaid to do according to all that his Father <hi>David</hi> did: Upon which account alſo, <hi>viz.</hi> of Religion and Piety moſt of all it is, that <hi>David</hi> himſelf was ſaid to be a Man after God's own heart.</note> But it was well done of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to encourage the Miniſters of the Law, by command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the People to give them their Portions; therefore it is well done ſtill of godly Princes, to encourage the Miniſters of the Goſpel, by commanding the People to pay them their Dues.</p>
            <p>Neither <hi>Hezekiah, Nehemiah,</hi> nor any other godly Prince or Ruler, hath thought fit at any time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was zealous in this matter, even unto Contention, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.10, 11, 12.</note> to require the Prieſts to attend their Service, without commanding unto them their juſt Maintenance. Yea, God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41771:8"/>looks not with any Man to ſerve any Office in his Houſe for Nought, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.10. Neither will God accept of any Man to pretend to the doing of his Work, that ſhall diſdain to receive his Wages. I am a great King, ſaith the <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Mal. 1.13. As he diſdains to be meanly dealt with by his People, that pretend unto him, ſo is it not his manner to deal meanly by his Prieſts that ſerve him; as you may ſee throughout that whole Chapter.</p>
            <p>Yea, our bleſſed Saviour in his Goſpel, ſaith, at the ſending of the ſeventy Diſciples, That <hi>the Labourer is worthy of his Hire:</hi>
               <note place="margin">St. <hi>Paul</hi> thinks fit to cite this Text of our Saviour, together with ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from <hi>Moſes,</hi> to prove both Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Maintenance to be due to the Goſpel-Miniſtery. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. verſ. 17, 18.</note> And will any man that is a Chriſtian, call him that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laboureth, an Hireling for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his Hire? If any man do, is not that man's Eye evil, becauſe our bleſſed Saviour is good? St. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. affirms, that for people to expect that their Miniſters ſhould attend, and ſerve them for nothing,
<note place="margin">An unreaſonableneſs hardly to be imagined, much leſs to be practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> except it were by ſuch as were accounted Tyrannous, and ſo accounted moſt of all for this, <hi>viz.</hi> That they were both envious, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurious to the Gods.</note> is a thing ſo unjuſt, and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that it is hardly to be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined. It were ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing as it would be, to make the Oxe tread out the Corn, and yet to muzzle his Mouth the while.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, I do not deny, but that a man may, and ought upon occaſions, ſerve in the Miniſtry between God and the People, without challenging any Portion or ſet Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance at all: But then at the ſame time, and notwithſtanding thoſe occaſions, he ought to be ſo far from either diſdaining that Maintenance to himſelf, or hindring of it unto others, that he ought to maintain and juſtifie the Right and Power of it, not only unto others that do receive it, but alſo to himſelf,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41771:9"/>though he receive it not. This was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s practice, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.4, 5. Though he wrought with his Hands, rather than he would be chargeable to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> becauſe of falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that perverted them to his prejudice, yet did he juſtifie unto them, that he had power to forbear working as well as others the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt were wont to do.</p>
            <p>What St. <hi>Paul</hi> did in this matter, he did out of Zeal to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Goſpel, and not out of Envy to hinder any man's juſt Right or Title,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Have we not power, <hi>viz.</hi> that power which is of Right?</note> and leaſt of all that of the Miniſters of Chriſt unto their own: Yea, leſt any one ſhould conſtrue him in ſuch a ſence, he ſhews himſelf earneſt in their Defence.</p>
            <p>There are divers poor Incumbents in theſe dayes, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to imitate St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this, as far as their occaſions may permit, receiving leſs, and paying more than the Due,
<note place="margin">Leſs than the Due from ſome of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and more than the Due to ſome Officers.</note> nevertheleſs are quiet and ſilent in favour of the Goſpel. And yet they are not Apoſtles as St. <hi>Paul</hi> was, at liberty to go far and near; but confin'd to certain Pariſhes and Places, and therefore not in a capacity, like St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to take of one Church wherewithal to ſerve another, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8, 9. They muſt either receive in ſome meaſure their Dues from their own Pariſhes, or elſe they can challenge none at all; to ſay nothing of the many Duties they pay out of what they do receive, to one, and to another.</p>
            <p>I have inſiſted the longer upon this Inſtance drawn out of the Words of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> on purpoſe to take you off from thinking the worſe of Tyth-paying, for its being expreſt, and ſet forth in the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Every thing that is written there, is not Ceremonial, in ſuch manner as to vaniſh quite at our Saviour's coming in the Fleſh, and to abide no longer. The
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41771:9"/>Law given by <hi>Moſes</hi> was threefold, Moral, Judicial, and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial. One and the ſame thing may in divers reſpects, partake of theſe three Laws. I will take the Subject in hand for inſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> Tyth-paying. As it is a Maintenance to the Prieſt-hood,
<note place="margin">No Sabbath without an Aſſembly; no Aſſembly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Miniſtry, no ſetled Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry without a Maintenance, <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.3. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.</note> or Miniſtery, ſo it is Moral, in as much force now as ever: As it was appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated unto the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> ſo it was Ceremonial, and in that reſpect it is aboliſh't: The Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> have no more to do with it now than other men may have.</p>
            <p>In the third of <hi>Malachy,</hi> the Obſervation of this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tyth-paying, is eſtabliſh't with a ſolemn Bleſſing, and the Violation of it threatned with a ſevere Curſe. If it had been a meer Ceremony (ſuch as ſome men would have it to be) the Prophet would not have buſied himſelf much about it. Where do you find the Prophets ſo greatly to concern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Ceremonies, as either to bleſs, or curſe in their behalf?</p>
            <p>And that you make not light of this Argument; the Fathers in the Council of <hi>Tibur</hi> (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi>) us'd for Tyth-paying no other Argument,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Patres in Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio Tiburienſi,</hi> cap. 13.</note> or Reaſon but this. Tythes (ſay they) are to be pay'd, that God being appeaſed, may the more plenteouſly beſtow things neceſſary upon us. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo at the Council of <hi>Mentz,</hi> did uſe the ſame Reaſon. Tythes, ſay they,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Patres in Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio Moguntino,</hi> cap. 11.</note> are to be pay'd, leſt God withdraw things neceſſary from us. In ſaying thus, they did not then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the Right of Tythes, which was determined long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but they perſwaded men in paying of Tythes to deal juſtly and truly, devoutly alſo,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. libro Hom.</hi> 48. <hi>Majores noſtri,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and conſcionably. Saith St. <hi>Aug.</hi> Our Anceſtors abounded with great Plenty, becauſe they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41771:10"/>pay'd Tyth devoutly and truly. Our [Anceſtors] ſaith he; which implies, that Tyth-paying was of common uſe long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s Dayes.</p>
            <p>Thus I have done with the ſecond Member of my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> that Tyth-paying was expreſly commanded in the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now of the third Member, <hi>viz.</hi> that it hath not been forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſince, nor any way abrogated, or done away. Which I prove thus:</p>
            <p>Whatſoever is made void at the coming of Chriſt in the Fleſh, either falls void of it ſelf, or elſe was declar'd void ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles: But Tyth-paying neither fell void of it ſelf, nor was declar'd void either by Chriſt or his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; therefore it was not made void at all. The Minor Propoſition, or that Tyth-paying fell not away upon either of the fore-mentioned accounts, I prove by Parts; and firſt, that it fell not away of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>What may conſiſt with Chriſt already given and exhibited, that falls not away of it ſelf; but Tyth-paying may conſiſt with Chriſt already given and exhibited; therefore it falls not away of it ſelf. The Minor I prove:</p>
            <p>What is neither Sacrament nor Sacrifice of the Law, that may conſiſt with Chriſt already given and exhibited: But Tyth-paying is neither Sacrament nor Sacrifice of the Law; therefore it may conſiſt with Chriſt already given and exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Or thus: Only ſuch things may not conſiſt with Chriſt given and exhibited, as made up the Partition-Wall, that was between God and Man firſt, and then between Men and Men, <hi>i. e.</hi> between the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles:</hi> But Tyth-paying was no part of that Partition-Wall: It parted not between God and Man, for it was God himſelf that did appoint it; it parted not between the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> becauſe both did pay Tyth to their Prieſts.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41771:10"/>
            <p>Tyth was pay'd generally in the world, before any Partition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> was in being;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin.</hi> lib. 12. cap. 14.19. <hi>Nat. Hiſt. Theophraſt.</hi> lib. 9. cap. 4. <hi>de Plantis. Iſocrates</hi> in commending the Wiſdom and Piety of <hi>Bufiris,</hi> the firſt King of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> doth inſtance in this as a main evidence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>viz.</hi> that he fixt a ſure and large Revenue upon the Prieſts, exempting them from Wars, and other Incumbrances; thinking he could not do too much for thoſe that ſerved in Holy things. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Iſocratis de Buſiride Orat.</hi>
               </note> as you may ſee, if you conſult <hi>Pliny</hi> in his natural Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, <hi>Iſocrates, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus,</hi> and others. Saith <hi>Alſtedius</hi> of things abrogated by the Death of Chriſt; That common ſaying muſt be of credit, <hi>viz.</hi> That the bloud of Chriſt once ſhed, forbids any more bloud to be ſhed in Sacrifice: Now in Tyth-paying there is no bloud, except it be the Heart-bloud of the prophanely covetous, which makes them even Mad to the Robbing of God.</p>
            <p>Neither is Tyth-paying a Sacrifice in any other ſence, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that it is Euchariſtical, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> it is a Sacrifice of Praiſe, and Thankſgiving.
<note place="margin">What is ſpent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Divine worſhip, is by a wiſe Man thought Gain. <hi>Plaut. de Milite.</hi>
               </note> He that will not acknowledge God in all his ways, to the intent that he may direct his Paths; nor honour God with his ſubſtance, with a Dependance upon him, let him pay no Tythes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5, 6.9, 10.</p>
            <p>How Witty are ſome prophane Ones now a dayes (ſome Poor, and others Rich) to upbraid the moſt Laborious of Chriſt's Miniſters,
<note place="margin">As the Heathens did phanſie to themſelves a variety of Gods, and every God an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſome earthly benefit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; ſo did they honour every ſuch God with a ſpecial part of that benefit whereof they ſuppoſed him to be the Author: As <hi>Lyaeus</hi> with the Fruit of the Vine; <hi>Ceres</hi> with the Fruits of the Earth; <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva</hi> with Oyl, <hi>&amp;c. Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor.</hi> lib. 8. Fab. 5.</note> the one with their Labour, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their Eſtates! (A Reproach moſt grievous unto ingenuous Men, ſuch as the Miniſters of Chriſt ought to be.) Holy <hi>Jacob</hi> was far from this; what he gave unto God, he called not his Labour, much leſs his Eſtate; but God's Gift. He ſaith not unto
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41771:11"/>God, of all that I ſhall labour for, or of all that I ſhall get; but of all that thou ſhalt give me, I will give the Tenth unto thee.</p>
            <p>Thus, I think, I have prov'd, that Tyth-paying falls not of it ſelf, at the Death of Chriſt, becauſe it may conſiſt with it; yea, it is a real Thankſgiving unto God, for the grace and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of it.</p>
            <p>Now it is my part to prove, that Chriſt did not declare it void in his Life time, <hi>i. e.</hi> while he was upon Earth. He's ſo far from that, that he enjoyn'd the Practice of it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. from the 37. <hi>verſe</hi> to the 43. He omitteth the waſhing of his Hands before Dinner, though it were to the Offence of the <hi>Phariſee</hi> that invited him to his Houſe. He's ſo far from ſaying, that that ought not to be left undone, that he defends the Omiſſion of it; as he did alſo in another place, the rubbing of the Ears of Corn by his Diſciples on the Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day: So little regard had he for either humane Traditions, or needleſs Ceremonies. But of Tyth-paying even to the ſmalleſt things, he ſayeth, theſe things ye ought not to leave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</p>
            <p>It is much to be conſidered, that when our bleſſed Saviour had ſpeech of the greateſt and weightieſt things of all, Faith, Judgment, and Mercy, that at the ſame time, and as it were in the ſame Paragraph, where he ſaith, that the one ought to be done, he ſaith alſo, that the other ought not to be left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</p>
            <p>How you may underſtand this ſpeech of our Saviour, I know not, but Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> ſaith, that the Primitive Church did generally underſtand it to be ſpoken in Confirmation of Tyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paying: To the Proof of which, he quotes St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, and St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> for the <hi>Latine.</hi> The ſpeech indeed was deſign'd firſt, and principally for Faith,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41771:11"/>Judgment, and Mercy; but then it was acceſſorily and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally for juſtneſs and exactneſs in paying of Tyths. If he had not meant that Tythes ſhould be pay'd, he would either have oppos'd them, as he did many Traditions and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; or elſe at the leaſt he would have ſaid nothing of them, thereby to ſuffer them to fall of themſelves.</p>
            <p>Now remains only the third part of the Propoſition to be prov'd, <hi>viz.</hi> That Tyth-paying was not declar'd void by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
            <p>If the Apoſtles declar'd Tyth-paying null and void, then that Declaration of their's is to be found either in their Acts written of them, or in their Epiſtles written by them. But it is to be found neither in the one, nor in the other: Therefore not at all.</p>
            <p>The Minor propoſition I leave to be diſprov'd by you, <hi>viz.</hi> By ſhewing where ſuch Declaration of the Apoſtles is to be found. They do declare againſt Circumciſion, Sacrificing, the Prieſthood of <hi>Levi,</hi> making a Difference in Meats and Drinks, and Dayes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe were ſhadows of things to come; whereas Tyth was nothing elſe but a Political Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance aſſign'd of God, to the uſe of thoſe that did ſerve at the Altar.</p>
            <p>If you ſay that as the Altar is now down, ſo muſt the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance go down with it. I anſwer, that as the Goſpel is up in the room of the Altar, ſo muſt the Maintenance ſtand up with it, though not in ſuch things as were but Occaſional, and did belong unto Sacrificing; yet in ſuch things as are Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental, and do relate unto Bleſſing. Though <hi>Levi</hi>'s Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing be paſt and gone, yet <hi>Melchiſedek</hi>'s Bleſſing is ſtill in being.</p>
            <p>If you allow that thoſe which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>In Tyth men pay not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what they have not, but according to what they have, which is the greateſt Equity that can be: there the Rich is not ſpared, nor the Poor oppreſt.</p>
                  <p>The benefit, <hi>viz.</hi> without a bleſſing, which might be made of the ceaſing of Tyth-paying, whoſe ſhould it be? the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords or the Tenants! I will not determine, becauſe I think the thing it ſelf in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is hardly to be ſuppos'd, and that upon many and ſeveral ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, though the Clergy only are upbraided by the Envious and Prophane; and among the Clergy, thoſe that labour moſt in the Word and Doctrine.</p>
               </note> and yet deny Tyth-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; can you ſhew any other way that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41771:12"/>may be more juſt, and equal than this, and no leſs certain and ſtedfaſt? A Fixt-Miniſtry, ſuch as that of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is, muſt have alſo a Fixt-Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. As Princes and Rulers are God's Miniſters in things of Juſtice, ſo are Goſpel-Preachers God's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the things of Religion and Worſhip. Now, as Tribute is due to Princes for their continual Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the things of Juſtice: So is a juſt Maintenance due to Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Preachers for their continual At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on the things of the Goſpel. Render to all their Dues; Tribute to whom Tribute, cuſtom to whom, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>As Incumbent Miniſters are confin'd to a certain Place, ſo are they alſo confin'd to their Calling. It is not free for them to ſhift themſelves out of it, as others may do out of theirs. They are barr'd from having Trades, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> had, yea, from uſing of Merchandiſe, or any other means of Lively-hood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confin'd to this one thing. And would you pretending to be Tender Chriſtians (for a man cannot be a great Chriſtian, but that he muſt be tender too) would you, I ſay, that Princes and Rulers that are Chriſtians, ſhould be ſo unreaſonable as to confine men, free born, freely educated, and brought up with much coſt and expence to a certain Calling (which is for the good of all men) and not provide that they may live thereof, as may become that calling?</p>
            <p>But you will not have Princes and Magiſtrates to appoint un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in this matter;
<note place="margin">There are many things lawful not only to be done by Chriſtians, but alſo to be commanded them by their Superiors, that have leſs Authority from the Scriptures than Tythes may have. From ſome mens im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent requiring of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for every humane Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, Doctor <hi>Sanderſon</hi> obſerves that the miſ-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Doctrine of the perfection of the Scriptures, occaſions much of Errour relating unto things indifferent, ſpecially in things of Prudence and Policy. As if Magiſtrates might not ordain in theſe things, but what they can ſhew Scripture for: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is enough that they ordain nothing againſt the Scripture.</note> you will be free in the things of God, <hi>viz.</hi> to Rob him if you pleaſe: As if it were not the chiefeſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41771:12"/>concern of Princes, to provide and ſee, that God be not rob'd either of the truth of his Service, or of the juſt Maintenance that belongs thereunto. Shall ſome few private men perſwade them, that a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing can reſt long upon this Nation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Miniſtry; or that to Oppreſs and Beggar the Miniſtry, be the way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the Bleſſing which this Land has ſo long enjoy'd? I think, they will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur that Sentence againſt themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe which deſpiſe him <hi>ſhall be lightly eſteemed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30. Shall God himſelf appoint unto you in his own things? Or hath he not done it already? If that which we contend for be not of his appointment, ſhew any thing elſe that he hath appointed in the place of it. Tyth to be once his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you acknowledge; ſhew where, and how he hath quitted that Right of his, and what he hath taken in exchange of it, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> what he hath ordain'd to ſucceed Tyth in the Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Miniſtry?</p>
            <p>Either Tythes are God's Right of propriety ſtill, or elſe he hath taken ſomething elſe in exchange of them,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>Saith Doctor <hi>Williams,</hi> God hath commanded the Tenth of all the increaſe of Goods to be pay'd out, thereby to ſhew that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a Chiefery of every thing unto himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Of the ſufferings of the Saints, <hi>p.</hi> 29.</p>
               </note> or elſe he hath no propriety at all, and conſequently, he hath nothing now wherein he may be rob'd; And if there be nothing wherein God may be rob'd, then is there no ſuch ſin as Sacriledge. Oh how fain would prophane Miſers that Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhould be no ſin! Whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes it to be as great a ſin, if not greater, than Idolatry, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. There is no ſin that blaſphemes the Name of God more than this.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:41771:13"/>
            <p>If God had now under the Goſpel no propriety wherein he might be rob'd; why doth St. <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 6. (where he bids thoſe that are <hi>taught in the word, communicate unto</hi> thoſe <hi>that teach them in all good things</hi>) give warning in the next Verſe, that they ſhould not <hi>deceive</hi> themſelves, as if God might be mock't? Now if in point of Right and Propriety, God were not concern'd in what Chriſtian people do communicate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Miniſters, how might he be mock't therein? For God to be mock't, and to be rob'd, I think is one and the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>If you acknowledge that God hath a Right of Propriety in any part or portion of his Bleſſings unto you;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod debebat Abraham Deo,</hi> &amp;c. What <hi>Abraham</hi> ow'd to Ged, that he pay'd into the Hands of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedek. Calvin</hi> on the Epiſt. to the <hi>Hebr.</hi> cap. 7. verſ. 4.</note> you muſt needs alſo grant, that his Miniſters have a Right to uſe that part, or portion of his, <hi>(viz.)</hi> of his Gift, and Aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I have prov'd this already, <hi>Num.</hi> 18. at the eight and thirtieth Verſe.</p>
            <p>§. <hi>2d.</hi> I have prov'd that Tyth falls not of it ſelf, as being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Death of Chriſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.18.</note> It is not in that reſpect either weak or unprofitable that it ſhould be abrogated. I have prov'd alſo, that our bleſſed Saviour has not declar'd againſt it, but for it. The like I have prov'd by the Apoſtles; ſaving that they have not us'd the Word [Tyth] or [Tenth] in this matter. To this you'l add, that they receiv'd not Tythes themſelves. And in this you triumph againſt us, as if we were contrary to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
            <p>That none of the Apoſtles at any time, or in any place, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd any manner of Tyth, I think is more than you can prove. Certain it is, that they did receive, and that both in a plentiful meaſure, and in an Honourable manner too. Of their Receipts, they were not only able to maintain themſelves,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41771:13"/>but alſo to ſuccour others. They commanded Collections to be made over whole Regions,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2, 3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3.</note> and Countries, and directed them to be ſent to all places, where the Exigency of the Brethren did require Relief. In ſhort, they did as the occaſion of their Apoſtleſhip did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; And the People did by them as the difficulties of thoſe times did permit. The People did then pay their Tithes unto others, the <hi>Jews</hi> to the <hi>Levites,</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to the Idol Prieſts.</p>
            <p>What ſhould the Apoſtles do in thoſe days with Tithes, whenas they were not fixt to any certain Place, nor tyed to any certain Congregation of People? What ſhould twelve men do with the Tith of the whole World?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.15.</note> From <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> unto <hi>Rome,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> was not out of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but all along as he went among the Chriſtians, he might command what he pleas'd.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.37.</note> What could the Apoſtles then have more, than to have the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at their Service, and what they had at their diſpoſe? The People ſold their poſſeſſions, and laid the price of them at the Apoſtles Feet.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles were ſo far from being Poor, that they were in a capacity to provide for the Poor. Yea, they were beyond the ſerving of Tables; they muſt have Officers under them for that, whilſt they ſhould attend a higher work, <hi>viz.</hi> Praying, and the Miniſtry of the Word, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.4.</p>
            <p>Will you have the Chriſtian Church to be always in its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy? Will you have the World generally to be either <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> or Heathen, and but a few converted unto Chriſt? Will you have Kings and Princes to be Perſecutors of the Chriſtians, for being ſuch? Will you have Idol-Prieſts to abound in every place, and will you have the People to be Idolaters? If ſo; then were there need that your Miniſters ſhould be Apoſtles, and you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41771:14"/>your ſelves ſuch Chriſtians as thoſe were, that laid the price of their Poſſeſſions at the Apoſtles feet. Or will you not rather give God thanks that the Church is ſpread throughout the World, that whole Nations are become profeſſedly Chriſtian, Kings and Queens are become Nurſing-Fathers, and Nurſing-Mothers; Idol Prieſts vaniſh't, and the People turn'd from I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, to ſerve the living God? In this condition, the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us hath not need of Apoſtles, but ordinary Miniſters; not of Apoſtles, to lay the Foundation, but of Miniſters, to build thereon: Miniſters orderly call'd, and ordinarily appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſucceed one the other in all the Parts and Diviſions which are made throughout the Land; which Diviſions, we call Pariſhes.</p>
            <p>Now will any ſober minded man deny a certain, known Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to be due unto every man from the place where he is bound to give his Attendance?
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12.</note> Saith St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthans, If others are partakers of this power over you, are not we</hi> much <hi>rather?</hi> So ſay I; If Impropriators and Farmers be partakers of this power of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Tythes from Pariſhes, are not we much rather? And yet we are only troubled by you, that labour among you, and are willing to live peaceably;
<note place="margin">Why do you not rather ſuffer wrong? Why do you not rather ſuffer your ſelves to be defrauded?</note> ſo willing, that we ſuffer our ſelves not only to be defrauded, but alſo openly wrong'd and injur'd: and with theſe doings ye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud your ſelves for Perfection, cry out upon us for Perſecution.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6.</note> But to the matter in hand. The Apoſtles expected not that the Church in all ſucceeding Ages ſhould be ſupplyed with Apoſtles as they were. Saith St. <hi>Paul</hi> of Chriſt after his Aſcenſion, <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 411.</note> and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtours and Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41771:14"/>
            <p>Though Paſtours and Teachers do ſucceed the Apoſtles in the Miniſtry,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>As the Apoſtles were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily called and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to their Miniſtry; ſo were they alſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily provided the neceſſaries of life: Which extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are ceas'd to the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Miniſters.</p>
                  <p>The like either of the one, or of the other is not to be expected again; except there ſhould be a new Goſpel to be Preacht, and new Miracles to be wrought.</p>
               </note> yet in a ſtrict ſenſe are they not Apoſtles as they were: and therefore in diverſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances the ſame things are not to be expected from them: No new Goſpel, no Revelation, no Miracles, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither muſt they expect from the People ſuch things, as the Apoſtles did, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to have the People every where at their Service, and what things they have at their diſpoſe. But as they are ſtinted in their Miniſtry, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to build on the Foundation which the Apoſtles have laid; ſo are they ſtinted alſo in their Maintenance, not to command what they pleaſe, but to receive what is appointed unto them, and that not every where, but only from the place where they are appointed to ſerve.</p>
            <p>By that time the Miniſtry came to be in Paſtours and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Goſpel was ſpread far and near, the World was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally become Chriſtian, and the Chriſtian Church had Peace and quietneſs in many Lands and Nations, Kingdoms, and States; then the Chriſtians being thus ſpread and multiplied were glad alſo to encreaſe the number of their Teachers, divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves into ſuch parts and parcels, Pariſhes and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, as that they might conveniently be ſerved by them.</p>
            <p>Pariſhes, and Decimations, or Tith-payments, were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore held to be Reciprocal, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> implying one another: And ſtill we ſay not, the Tith of the Lordſhip or of the Mannor, but the Tith of the Pariſh: and yet Tith was paid long before Lands and Nations were divided into Pariſhes, yea, before they were divided into Biſhopricks; nay, before the Church had
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41771:15"/>perfect Peace or Quietneſs. And not only ſo, but Churches alſo were endow'd by devout perſons,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. Eccl. Hiſt.</hi> lib. 9. cap. 8. <hi>Origen</hi> affirmeth, that the Commandment for Tyth paying ought ſtill to ſtand according to the Letter of it. In his 11. <hi>Hom.</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Num.</hi> 18. And <hi>Clem Alexandrinus</hi> who liv'd very near the firſt Century, affirms the Tenth of the Fruits, and other Encreaſe to be due to the Prieſts. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Men and Women, even in the midſt of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. This is ſtoried to be done in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Trajan</hi>'s days; yea, before his dayes no man can tell how ſoon they began; they were always in doing, notwithſtanding the greateſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions.</p>
            <p>But before I can go on with my Argument, I muſt return to the Apoſtles again; between whom, and the ſucceeding Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and Teachers, I have ſhew'd to be a great difference; of which difference, thoſe that are prophanely greedy, as envious to the calling of the Miniſtry, as they are Miſerable to detain their Dues, will take notice: And yet they will have them to agree in this one thing, <hi>viz.</hi> That the preſent Paſtors and Teachers have no more Houſe and Home than ſome of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had. That we ſhould have the like Liberty, Command, and Authority as they had, they would not wiſh by any means. That we have not theſe things as they had is, I think, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Argument, that though it might be prov'd that they receiv'd not Tyths, yet it doth not thence follow, that we ought not to receive them.</p>
            <p>If they receiv'd not Tyths in thoſe early dayes of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet others did: As the <hi>Levites</hi> among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol-Prieſts among the Heathens. As they did continue their Prieſt-hood, ſo did they alſo continue to receive their Tythes. Though they were void <hi>de Jure,</hi> yet <hi>de Facto,</hi> they were not, until they were declar'd, and made known to be ſo: And then ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi> a Proteſtant Writer, the Tyths were taken from them, and confer'd upon the Goſpel-Miniſters.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41771:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſtellus,</hi> a very Learned Man, ſaith in his Book, wherein he treats of ſuch things as the whole World is agreed on, that it is a Natural Principle, an inbred Notion to every man, that ſets not himſelf to reſiſt even the Light that is within him, to think it reaſonable that out of the yearly Encreaſe that God gives him in his Goods and Subſtance, he ſhould return a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that as a Holy Tribute to the Maintenance of God's pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Worſhip and Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am a great King, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and my Name is dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful among the Heathen,</hi> Mal. 1.14. When was the time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Give unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſars, <hi>and unto God the things that are Gods.</hi> Saith Mr <hi>Leigh,</hi> It is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in this place, that the Article is twice repeated in the <hi>Greck</hi> Text, when our Saviour ſpeaks of God, and but once when he ſpeaks of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> ſhewing our ſpecial care ſhould be, to give God his Due. <hi>Annot.</hi> p. 50.</note> or where was the place, that God's Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty was not acknowledg'd, <hi>viz.</hi> by giving unto him the things that are his? You know that in the late Troubles, Tyths were pay'd without diſpute. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are not the only Men now a dayes that are concern'd in Tyths; they have no Perſonal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in them; they neither deſcend unto them from their Anceſtors, nor yet go down from them to their Poſterity: They are to them only a Maintenance to their calling, and a Reward to their Service; and that in many places ſo ſlender an Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, by reaſon of Impropriations, and other Deductions,
<note place="margin">Not only Poverty, but alſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, which by the ruder ſort is uſually caſt upon it, ſhould not be grievous unto a good Clergy-man, but that it doth diſable him divers wayes, both Spiritually and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally rendring him the leſs profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto thoſe, whoſe concern it is to ſubmit themſelves unto him, and to receive profit by him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> that while they live, they do but hardly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and when they dye, they leave not wherewithal to pay a Mortua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Nor do I ſee the generality of People to love them the more for being poor, nor the readier to pay them their Dues for being ſmall; but ſo much the bolder either to detain them from them, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41771:16"/>elſe to diminiſh them unto them: Though indeed thoſe that are truly Religious, and conſequently well-will'd to the calling, may have a Tenderneſs for them upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>What was in the World of a known Right, and conſtant Practice, all along before the Law was given by <hi>Moſes;</hi> What was expreſly commanded in that Law, and of which there has been no Prophecy that it ſhould ceaſe at any time; What did no way typifie Chriſt to come in the fleſh, and now that he is come, doth not derogate therefrom; What hath not been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd voyd, either by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles; What was no part of the Partition-Wall that was between <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> What ceaſed not with the Jewiſh-Church and Common-Wealth, but continued in the Lands and Nations among whom the <hi>Jews</hi> were diſperſt: What the Primitive Chriſtians did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver diſown as to the matter of Right, and for Practice, did put in uſe as ſoon as conveniently they might, mean-while ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church even with the Sale of their Lands and Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: What the Law of the Land moſt Religiouſly commands, threatning moſt ſevere Puniſhment unto thoſe that fail; What is not only lawful in it ſelf, but alſo expedient for you (for a payment of greater Equity you cannot deviſe,) That judge you, if you may not part with, with a ſafe conſcience, <hi>viz.</hi> without fear of diſpleaſing God in ſo doing.</p>
            <p>While you tarry for further ſatisfaction (if you deſire any) by an impartial Reading of other learned mens Works,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>I have publiſhed this little Tract, on purpoſe to beg this Condeſcenſion at Learned Mens hands. And I beſeech you, ſhew not your ſelves ſo deſperate, as to render their Labour loſt that ſhall travel to do you good.</p>
                  <p>The gain ſaying of Tyth is indeed but an Out-work of your Sect: yet is it the main thing that you truſt unto; as being both an In let to the Greedy and Prophane to come in unto you; and alſo an Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of Obliquies and prophane Speeches, to the diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Religion and Piety.</p>
               </note> either ſet forth already, or to be ſet forth hereafter purpoſely for your uſe, and to your capacity; I think you can do no leſs than ſuffer your Tyths to be had from you in quietneſs, out of Tenderneſs, Firſt, to the word of God, of whoſe Sentence in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41771:16"/>this caſe you muſt needs be doubtful at the leaſt: Secondly, of opppſing the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and conſtant practice of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world for the ſpace of fourteen hundred years and upwards: and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of controuling the Law of the Land wherein you live, the reſiſting where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is Self-damnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2. And yet indeed to watch you leading Home your Corn, is both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly, and difficult; and then to take what you do not lay out, is not proper to be done.</p>
            <p>Be perſwaded to lay out your Tyths as others do, that ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours you may make way for that Bleſſing to light upon us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, could not deviſe a better Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to deſtroy Chriſtianity, than by taking away the Maintenance of the Miniſtry.</note> which God hath promiſed unto thoſe that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him with their ſubſtance, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.10.</p>
            <p>I think you not ſo ſtupid, as not to take notice of the juſtneſs of God's providence in theſe late years, altering greatly both the Weather,
<note place="margin">You'l ſay, far be it from you to ſeek the deſtruction of Chriſtianity: I ſay ſo too; yea, ſo far as not to endeavour any ſuch thing, the juſt and plain conſequence whereof, may impair, or but occaſion any the leaſt detriment unto it. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, it is reported of your Teachers, that they make but light even of the perſon of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: What then do they make of his Office, and what wonder is it that they teach you, to caſt off his Inſtitutions, <hi>viz.</hi> his Word, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> making uſe of you to cry Hirelings againſt us; whilſt they privily (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) and I preſume, unawares to many of you, <hi>do bring in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Hereſies, denying even the Lord that bought them,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. O let them not under pretence of the power of Chriſt within you, perſwade you to make light of the Perſon of Chriſt without you, it is Chriſt without you that hath bought you. Honour him as ye ought, and deſpiſe his Inſtitutions if you can.</note> and the Fruits of the Earth, from what they were wont to be. This is occaſion'd by our Miſ-doings, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the which, I think no Man will reckon Tyth-paying, it being not only juſtifiable in it ſelf, but alſo Commendable, and withall, of a longer ſtanding, than that any ſuch thing may be laid to its charge. What may be thought of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>viz.</hi> Gain-ſaying of Tyth, a Novelty, and that a dangerous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41771:17"/>one too, I leave to you to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord, and the King, and meddle not with thoſe that are given to change,</hi> Prov. 24.21, 22. And yet, what you would have, may not properly be ſaid to be a change; for a change is of ſomething into ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or of one thing for another: But what you would have, (if you know what it is) is a bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſomething into nothing.</p>
            <p>If you will not be concern'd in theſe Words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> your Deſign aiming further than a change; be pleas'd to hearken to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> bidding you to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet,</hi> and to <hi>do your own buſineſs;</hi> which I think not to be that either of Church or State.</p>
            <p>Upon condition you ſtudy to be quiet in ſuch manner, that King and Kingdom, Church and State, Land and Nation, may be in quiet for you, I bid you heartily to Farewel.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41771:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
